大家好 我是《天天太空人》的Tim Dodd
Tim- Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
视频中的是太空叉的猛禽发动机 用于他们的星舰及其超重型助推器上
This is SpaceX's Raptor engine that powers is their Starship and SuperHeavy booster.
它运转起来的时候可老热了
When this thing is running, there is unbelievably hot combustion,
发动机中心持续进行着高温的燃烧
continually burning at the heart of this beast.
开氏温标
实际上 主燃烧室的燃气温度可以高达3500K
In fact, the gases inside the combustion chamber can reach about 3,500 K,
大约是太阳表面温度的一半
about half as hot as the surface of the sun,
几乎高于一切金属的熔点了
which is above the melting point of pretty much any material out there.
但正是这样的热量才让火箭发动机成为可能
But this heat is kind of what makes a rocket engine function.
毕竟火箭发动机本质上就是
I mean, after all their only real purpose
把燃料中的化学能转化为压力和热量
is to convert the chemical energy inside the propellant into pressure, and often therefore heat
从而产生推力
so they can produce thrust.
那么问题来了
And that brings up an obvious question.
发动机是怎样耐受如此高温的?
How in the heck do engines survive this heat?
火箭科学家们是如何制伏可以瞬间熔化甚至汽化燃烧室的金属材料的高温
How did rocket scientists figure out how to keep an engine running continuously
while harboring combustion inside that's hot enough to
同时还能保证发动机持续高速运转的?
not just melt the metal walls containing it, but actually vaporize the metal,
实际上这个高温可以让金属材料直接升华了
or more pedantically sublimate the metal from solid to a gas in an instant,
不过为了方便 熔化 汽化 升华 本视频统称为"熔化"了
but we'll just say melt for simplicity in this video.
那么今天咱们就来聊聊工程师们为了防止发动机熔化所采用的奇技婬巧
So today we're going to talk about the tricks engineers employ to keep rocket engines from melting.
以上为本期目录
Here's the timestamps to the sections we're going to be going over,
空降坐标
热沉冷却
混合比偏置冷却
烧蚀冷却
再生冷却
膜冷却
辐射冷却
总结
涉及热沉冷却 混合比偏置冷却 烧蚀冷却 再生冷却 膜冷却 辐射冷却
such as heat sinks, fuel to oxidizer ratios,
ablative cooling, regenerative cooling, film cooling and radiative cooling.
并且每种冷却方法都有相应的有趣的应用
And we're also going to be showing you some awesome examples of each of these as well.
当然如果你不爱看视频不想听我叭叭 想直接看文字内容
And if you're someone who would rather read about this, instead of hear me talk about it,
那么可以前往视频下方的链接看文字版
don't forget we do have an article version of this up at our website at everydayastronaut.com,
and there's a link in the description to that article.
火箭发动机 不惧火炼 何以为之?
Rocket engines, too cool to melt, but how?
视频中多次用到cool这个词的双关(冷的、凉爽的、酷酷的)
就不做详细翻译了
一同窥探究竟!
Let's get started.
热沉冷却
这是火箭发动机主燃烧室
This is a combustion chamber.
热沉冷却
顶部是喷注器
At the top of it is the injector face.
喷注器
氧化剂和燃料会在此以很高的压力注入主燃烧室
This is where the fuel and oxidizer get pumped into the chamber at very high pressures.
两者会在主燃烧室内喷注器下游某处混合
The fuel and the oxidizer will mix somewhere downstream of the injector face
inside of the combustion chamber,
然后点火燃烧
and they'll ignite and then combust,
假定在燃料和氧化剂流量供应充足的情况下
assuming there's adequate and continuous flow that repellents will burn.
但是在金属燃烧室室壁中充满了超高温的燃气
But with ridiculously hot gasses squeezed together in between the metal chamber walls,
我们又不希望金属室壁熔化
we certainly don't want the metal to melt.
因此或许最简单的办法就是把室壁做厚
So perhaps the easiest thing we can do is just make the metal walls so thick,
即使是高温燃气也不足以熔化所有金属
even the scorching hot gases can't heat up all the metal enough to actually melt it.
而这样的金属室壁 就充当了"热沉"的作用 或者说就是个导热器
The walls act, as what's known as a heat sink or a giant thermal conductor
heat sink
可以在全部金属部分都熔化掉之前的一定时间内承受一定热量
that can handle a high heat load for a period of time
before it warms up all of the metal to its melting point.
材料上可以使用一些合金
The use of exotic materials might be a fitting choice here.
SpaceX工厂使用铬镍铁合金制造猛禽发动机歧管
比如铬镍铁之类在高温下仍能保持强度的合金
Something that can handle extreme heat and still be strong, such as inconel or other alloys,
但当然 价格 重量等其他因素也不能忽略
but of course, price or weight or other factors certainly come into play.
首先 如果选择加厚金属室壁作为热沉
Obviously, first off, if you're using thick metal walls as a heat sink,
那一定会增加死重
they're going to be quite heavy.
在这个火箭工程师为了减重5%宁愿吃帽子的世界
And in a world where rocket engineers would eat a hat for even a 5% weight reduction,
你给发动机室壁增加厚度防止熔化这样的操作
making your engine's walls so incredibly thick they don't melt
简直是在开历史的倒车
is not only far from optimal, it's downright primitive.
另一个问题是 为了防止发动机熔化 要限制运行时间
The other problem is you can realistically only run an engine for so long
MOMO号火箭 12kN推力 液氧乙醇 挤压供应发动机 [未冷却]
另一个问题是 为了防止发动机熔化 要限制运行时间
before you eventually heat it all up to its melting point.
因此它天生就有局限性和可行性的问题
So it has inherent limitations and viability.
热沉冷却不太适合用在主发动机上
This option isn't a very good choice for main propulsion engines,
因为主发通常会持续运行好几分钟
where they might need to run for several minutes continuously.
但对于调姿发动机之类的小型发动机来说就很合适
But this option is actually valid for smaller engines, such as reaction control thrusters.
RCS
RCS发动机通常是脉冲点火 工作时间很短
Reaction control thrusters are often pulsed and run in shorter duration burns.
SpaceX Draco发动机点火测试 - 2010年
可以在脉冲间隔内有时间冷却
This allows them an opportunity to cool down between pulses.
阿波罗RCS测试
发动机设计可以简单可靠
This keeps them simple and reliable,
但为了防止发动机熔化 连续工作时间有限
but with limitations on continuous runtime to keep them from melting.
那么能不能降低燃烧的温度呢?
But what if you could just lower the temperature of the combustion?
燃气温度低一点 室壁就能造得薄一点
A less hot gas might make it so you could use thinner walls
燃烧时间也能延长了呀
and might make long duration burns more survivable.
混合比偏置冷却
没错 这招可行
Well, that actually is an option.
保护发动机的另一种相对简单的方法
The next relatively simple thing you can do to keep your engine intact
混合比偏置冷却
就是使用过量的燃料或氧化剂运行
is to simply run the engine with more fuel or more oxidizer
即"富燃"或"富氧"运行
otherwise known as fuel rich or oxidizer rich,
从而可以降低燃气温度
which can lower the temperature of the exhaust.
这个比例指燃料与氧化剂的质量比
This ratio is the fuel to oxidizer mass ratio.
若想让燃料100%完全燃烧干净
Now, if you want it to burn 100% of your propellant
氧化剂也完全参与反应
and have absolutely as much of it react with each other as possible,
就需要让两者以理想化学计量比进行反应
you'd need to burn it at what's known as its stoichiometric ratio.
此时氧化剂和燃料都刚好充分反应
This is where there's the exact amount of fuel and oxidizer
to perfectly react as completely as possible with each other,
没有多余的燃料未参与反应
which leaves no propellant left unburnt.
但以理想化学计量比进行反应也意味着完全榨干了化学键中的能量
But burning out your stoichiometric ratio also means
you're releasing as much heat from the chemical bonds as possible too.
这在某些情况下可能是有益的
While that might actually be ideal in some situations,
但对于火箭发动机来说却有些弊端
that is not ideal in a rocket engine for a few reasons,
发动机产生越多的热量
the more heat your engine is producing,
就需要采取更多手段来冷却发动机 防止其熔化
the more you need to cool your engine via other methods, so it doesn't melt
即采取本视频中多种手段结合的方法
and you're going to need to employ more of the tactics
that we're going to be discussing in this video.
因此 火箭发动机会工作在稍稍偏离理想化学计量比的条件下
So rocket engines need to run their fuel to oxidizer ratios a bit off from stoichiometric.
主燃烧室多为富燃燃烧
Main combustion chambers tend to run fuel rich
可以降低热量负担 并提高效率
because this usually results in lower thermal loads and higher efficiency,
而且炽热的富氧燃气是材料唯恐避之不及的东西
not to mention scorching hot gaseous oxygen is typically avoided as much as possible,
星舰SN8燃料罐压力过低 导致发动机富氧燃烧 绿色火焰为燃烧中的发动机铜制内衬
能把发动机直接熬成一锅粥
since it sure loves to turn metal into soup
属实是"富发动机"燃烧了
and the rocket engine will end up running engine rich
可不兴这么整
and that's definitely not good.
但除了主燃烧室可以应用混合比偏置冷却外
But beyond just the main combustion chamber's fuel to oxidizer ratio,
预燃室或者燃气发生器也可以使用非常富氧或富燃的环境来降低温度
you can also run your preburner or your gas generator
F-1发动机燃气发生器在NASA马歇尔太空飞行中心进行测试
预燃室或者燃气发生器也可以使用非常富氧或富燃的环境来降低温度
very fuel rich or oxidizer rich in order to keep it cool too.
实际上 它们中的混合比可以远远偏离主燃烧室的情况 从而保证温度更低
In fact, you can burn it at a different, more conservative, cooler temperature
than you would your main combustion chamber.
当然 如果你不清楚什么是预燃室或者燃气发生器
And quick side note, if you don't know what a preburner is or a gas generator,
本视频的双语字幕
@天外飞舰 av294439869
别怕 抱紧我
don't worry, I've got you covered.
来看这期讲苏联火箭发动机的视频
Check out my Soviet rocket engine video.
那期视频的开头我介绍了很多术语 对理解本期视频很有帮助
In the beginning in the glossary, I go over a lot of terms that will be really helpful for this video and
实际上对理解所有火箭发动机的视频都有帮助
frankly, all videos about rocket engines.
我们回到利用混合比偏置的方法冷却预燃室或燃气发生器的话题上来
Okay, back to keeping your preburner or gas generator cool with your fuel to oxidizer ratio.
这种操作非常重要 因为让高速旋转的涡轮保持冷却是很难的
This is extremely important because it's hard to cool a spinning turbine.
不管用什么材料都很难躲开积热的问题
You're really stuck with a set amount of heat that it can actually take based on the materials.
所以只能想办法调整混合比 让温度降低到材料能承受为止
And you just kind of simply have to change your fuel to oxidizer ratio until the heat load is bearable.
而且与主燃烧室的富燃情况不同
And unlike the fuel rich main combustion chambers,
涡轮可以运行在富燃或富氧环境下
turbines can be designed to run fuel rich or oxidizer rich.
比如航天飞机的RS-25主发动机的预燃室就是富燃燃烧的
For example, the Space Shuttle's RS-25 main engines ran fuel rich through their preburner,
而苏联设计的NK-33闭式循环发动机的预燃室则是富氧运行的
while the Soviet designed NK-33 ran oxidizer rich propellant through their close cycle preburners.
当然 以上所说这些火箭发动机的科学
But all of this is rocket science we're talking about
其本质就是性能与优化的调和的艺术
and performance and optimization is everything.
诚然 发动机死重越小越好
So we don't want a big heavy engine
不能一味追求冷却而放弃整体性能
or one that's sandbagging its performance to run cooler,
但发动机还不可以被热量熔化……真的不可以吗?
but we also don't want our engine to melt, or do we?
烧蚀冷却
谈下一话题! 一种非常简单高效的冷却发动机的方法
Welcome to perhaps one of the most simple and effective ways to cool an engine,
那就是让它熔化 但没有完全熔化
and that is, well to allow it to melt, but just a little bit.
即烧蚀冷却
This is called ablative cooling.
烧蚀冷却指使用会汽化的材料送入尾流中 并带走热量
Ablative cooling is where you use a material that will vaporize and gets thrown into the wake,
which takes the heat along with it.
烧蚀材料通常由碳复合材料制成 熔点高
It's most commonly made out of carbon composites, which have a very high melting point.
同样的原理还会应用在许多航天器的隔热罩上
This is also the same principle many spacecraft use on their heat shields.
当航天器再入大气时 会产生大量热量
When a spacecraft is coming back into the atmosphere for re-entry, it gets crazy hot.
猎户座飞行测试1 再入 [10倍速]
隔热罩会贴脸硬抗这个热量
And the heat shield just accepts that heat, it takes it right in the face.
当表面温度上升到一定程度时
And then when the surface gets too hot,
材料就会熔化 并随之带走热量
it basically melts a layer away, taking the heat with it.
防止热量继续渗透进航天器内部
This prevents heat from penetrating deeper into the vehicle.
同样的原理也可以用在火箭发动机上
And this is the same idea you can use to cool a rocket engine.
烧蚀冷却
即在主燃烧室和喷管的内壁上涂一层碳复合材料
Inside the metal walls of the combustion chamber and the nozzle
will be a layer of carbon composites.
碳复合材料层
随着燃料在发动机内燃烧 碳材料内衬会慢慢烧蚀掉
As the propellant burns inside the engine, the carbon liner will slowly get chewed away.
乍一听可能感觉不靠谱 我一开始直觉也是这样
Now, if you're anything like me, you might think this sounds like kind of a terrible idea,
但实际上这种冷却方案既高效又可靠
but it's actually an incredibly efficient and reliable method of cooling
因为设计本身是自控的 没有移动部件 效率还高
since it's self-regulating, has no moving parts and is incredibly effective,
但也存在一些限制
but it does have its limitations.
烧蚀冷却
显然 这样的发动机没法重复使用
Obviously, if you're looking to reuse your engine, you should probably look elsewhere.
而且实际上 一些发动机根本无法在使用前进行全程测试
In fact, some engines may not be able to go through their full testing before use
因为测试会消耗燃烧室壁上的烧蚀层
because it will wear down the ablative chamber walls.
同时 由于燃烧室和喷管喉部的室壁会变薄
And because the chamber and throat walls get thinner,
发动机整体性能也会随之降低
their performance can actually decrease throughout the burn
原因在于喉部面积相比喷管出口会越变越大
as your throat's area will increase a lot compared to the nozzle exit,
喉部
出口
导致发动机整体的膨胀比降低
which will decrease the overall expansion ratio of the engine,
膨胀比 = 出口面积 / 喉部面积
这对于想要飞出地球大气的火箭来说是非常不利的
which is the opposite of what you want as you ascend into thinner parts of the atmosphere.
该方法还会增加重量
And it's also quite heavy.
因为烧蚀层本身就是增加死重的附加物
The ablative material is just extra stuff that weighs a decent amount.
至于现实中的例子 最有名的可能就是阿波罗飞船上升级发动机了
Perhaps one of the most famous examples of this is the Apollo Lunar Ascent engine,
阿波罗17号登月舱上升级起飞
发动机无法在地面整体进行点火测试
which could not be test fired as a complete unit
只能等宇航员回家时才知道到底能不能用
before being lit on the surface of the moon to get astronauts home.
想想就吓人
Yes, that's a terrifying thought.
烧蚀冷却的另一个例子是太空叉的首款梅林发动机 梅林1A
Some other examples of ablatively cooled engines are SpaceX's first Merlin engine, the Merlin 1A,
SpaceX 梅林1A发动机全推力测试 [2010年]
在猎鹰一号 遥一和遥二箭上用过
which flew on the first two Falcon 1 flights
还有ULA家的Delta IV火箭主发动机 RS-68A
and United Launch Alliance's Delta IV engine, the RS-68A.
在RS-68A上 其实可以直接看出这款火箭是使用烧蚀冷却的
On the RS-68A, you can easily tell this engine is ablative
因为它是氢氧燃料火箭
because the engine runs on Hydro-Lox,
而通常氢氧机的尾焰是透明的 产物只有水
which usually has a nearly completely transparent exhaust of just water vapor,
就像视频中的航天飞机一样
like we saw on the space shuttle.
但RS-68A发动机的尾焰却是明亮的橙色
But the RS-68A's exhaust is bright orange
因为发动机排出的碳烧蚀材料会继续和大气中的氧反应 呈现这样的亮橙色
because the carbon that is ablated and ejected from the engine
continues to react with the oxygen in the atmosphere, which makes it burn bright orange.
有时一些RCS发动机也会使用烧蚀冷却的燃烧室
Sometimes reaction control thrusters use ablative chambers too,
双子座飞船OAMS [在轨调姿与机动系统]
通常用在短期任务里
since they are often used in short durations
有特定的燃料量 保证烧蚀材料够用
and have a set amount of propellant they can use before they run out.
工程师可以根据极限使用情况来设计烧蚀层的厚度
So engineers can design the wall thickness to match the maximum use case.
那么如果烧蚀冷却还是不够呢?
Okay, but what if ablative cooling is just not cool enough for you?
没事 咱这还有几招
Well, then we've got a few more options to check out.
再生冷却
可能液体火箭发动机最常用的方法就是再生冷却了
Perhaps the most common way to keep a liquid fueled rocket engine from melting
is by using regenerative cooling.
燃料的一部分或全部 会先流经发动机的喷管和燃烧室壁
This is where they flow some or all of the propellant
through the walls of the combustion chamber and the nozzle
之后才会由喷注器进入主燃烧室
before it goes through the injectors and into the chamber.
你没听错
Yeah, that's right.
即使火箭发动机的喷管和燃烧室壁看上去那么薄
Even though the walls and the nozzles of rocket engines look super thin,
但总有空间可供燃料在室壁流个来回进行冷却
there's often a very small channel
where fuel can run up and down the walls in order to keep them cool.
这是一项重大突破
This was a major breakthrough
火箭发动机从此多少有了无限运行的能力
that allowed rocket engines to run more or less indefinitely.
早期使用再生冷却的发动机会在主燃烧室外壁上
Early versions of regeneratively cooled engines would have the main chamber
铺一层可流动冷却剂或燃料的外衬
and then basically a liner on the outside of it to run the coolant or fuel through.
后来 大家直接变成使用管路来组成燃烧室壁了
Later it became common to actually just use pipes to form the walls of the combustion chamber.
实际上直到今天 RL10发动机也还在使用钎焊管束式结构
In fact, the RL10 engine still uses braze tube construction today,
只是工艺比当年更现代化了
although they are working on modernizing that process.
更现代的做法是在燃烧室壁和喷管壁内铣出一条冷却通道
A more modern practice is to mill a cooling channel
in the walls of the combustion chamber and the nozzle,
然后用铜或镍合金将其封闭
and then use a copper or a nickel alloy to close it off,
构成其内壁
and then that will be the inner wall of the chamber.
使用铜和镍合金是因为它们具有高导热性
Copper and nickel alloys are used because of their ability to transfer heat
可以有效将热量从壁面传入冷却剂
from the walls into the coolant, thanks to their high thermal conductivity.
这时你们可能会问: 这样不会让燃料在到达燃烧室之前就沸腾吗?
Now you might be asking, doesn't that boil the fuel before it reaches the chamber?
当然会啦
Yeah, it sure can.
而且实际上这个过程中沸腾的燃料还可以用来驱动发动机的涡轮泵
And this process of boiling the fuel can actually be used
to spin the turbines to run the pumps of the engines.
即"膨胀循环"
This is what the expander cycle is.
膨胀循环利用了燃料从液体到气体的热膨胀的能量
It harnesses the energy of the thermal expansion of the fuel going from liquid to gas.
效率极高 但会受到可用热量的限制
It is extremely efficient, but it is limited by the amount of available heat.
我将在未来的视频中再细讲膨胀循环
We'll talk more about the expander cycle in an upcoming video,
届时将介绍几乎所有的循环类型并探讨其优缺点
where we go over pretty much all of the cycle types and talk about their pros and cons.
大多数发动机使用燃料作为冷却剂 但也可以使用氧化剂
Most engines use the fuel as coolant, but oxidizer could be used as well.
有一件事特别有意思 就是当使用低温推进剂时
But a fun little thing to know is when cryogenic propellants are used,
火箭喷管的外壁温度可能会超级低
the outside walls of the rocket nozzles can be unbelievably cold,
同时喷管内部则是熊熊烈火
while the inside of the walls are scorching hot.
这内外壁温差得有多大呀!
Talk about a temperature gradient.
来看看视频中的RS-25发动机试车
Check out this video of an RS-25 running.
外壁我舔过了 是甜的 不信你们试试
If you went up and touch the outside of it, your hand would freeze solid,
而内侧 则是瞬间火化
touch the inside and it burned off instantly.
每每想起这种冰火两重天的场景都让我兴奋不已
It's honestly crazy to me that these two extremes can exist in such close proximity.
再生冷却的一大挑战是壁内压强需要大于燃烧室内压强
One of the challenges with regenerative cooling is that
the pressure inside the walls needs to actually be higher
再生冷却的一大挑战是壁内压强需要大于燃烧室内压强
than the pressure of the combustion inside the chamber.
你没听错
That's right.
火箭喷管薄薄的壁上无数细小通道内流动的低温液体
The tiny little channels flowing cryogenic fluids inside the thin little walls of a rocket nozzle
实际压强比主燃烧室本身还要高
are actually under higher pressure than the main combustion chamber itself.
因为这些壁内管路基本都是给喷注器供油的管道
This is because of the fact that the walls are essentially just tubes that feed the injectors
流体总会从高压流向低压
and pressure always flows from high to low.
因此 喷注器的压力总是要比燃烧室高
So the injectors always have to have higher pressure than the combustion chamber.
但我总感觉 那些小小壁内通道要承受如此高压力 实在是太震撼了
But it's just crazy to me that those tiny little passages inside the walls
need to handle that really high pressure too.
总感觉这样的薄壁 很容易出现泄漏的问题
Seems like with such thin walls, it'd be so easy to spring a leak.
但其实如果真泄露了也不怕
Well, if a leak does spring, there's some good news.
假如再生冷却的发动机燃烧室内壁出现了泄露
Let's pretend a leak springs on the inner wall of a regenerative cool chamber,
由于壁内压强高于燃烧室压强
because the pressure inside the walls are higher than the pressure inside the chamber,
所以结果就是燃料会向燃烧室内泄露 反而进一步提升冷却效果
all that will happen is fuel'll leak in a little and actually provide some additional cooling.
在我在德州奥斯汀的萤火虫工厂采访CEO Tom Markusic时他向我解释了此事
Firefly CEO, Tom Markusic, explained this to me
when I interviewed him at their factory outside of Austin, Texas.
萤火虫太空公司 CEO
- 是呀 发动机可太有意思了
- Yeah, engines are amazing.
我在这时间不长 但我曾经见过
I haven't seen this here as much, but I've seen places
发动机发生自我烧蚀 然后开始泄露
where the engine will actually erode itself down to the point where it starts leaking
然后就没事了 因为烧蚀情况不会恶化
and then it's happy, and it doesn't go any further.
就像在自我调节一样
It just like self regulates.
- 是呀 有意思
- Yeah, interesting.
停一下 如果燃料漏进了主燃烧室
But wait, if fuel leaks into the chamber,
为什么不会导致爆炸等更恶劣的情况呢?
how would that not just make it explode more and make an even bigger problem?
这种泄露是怎么保护发动机的呢?
How on earth can that help cool an engine?
隆重为大家介绍下一种冷却方法 膜冷却
Well, that brings us to our next method of cooling, film cooling.
膜冷却
膜冷却是另一种很常见的冷却方法
Another common method of cooling is film cooling.
即在燃烧室/喷管表面与高温燃气之间注入流体
This is where you inject a fluid between
the combustion chamber and nozzle surface and the hot combustion gases,
流体包括液体或气体
because don't forget, fluids are either gas or liquid.
所以使用液体和气体燃料都可以
So this can be done in either form with liquid or gaseous propellants.
背后的基本机制是在内壁和高温燃气之间
The basic mechanism at play is creating a boundary between the wall and the hot combustion gas
使用低温流体创造一个隔热的边界
that creates a thermal insulation with a cooler fluid in between them.
怎么做到的?
So how exactly do they do this?
我们先从液膜冷却开始
Well, let's start off with liquid film cooling.
膜冷却
进行液膜冷却的一个简单方法就是
One easy way to do liquid film cooling is to literally just
在喷注器盘面外圈设置较高浓度的燃料或氧化剂喷注
have a higher concentration of fuel or oxidizer injectors
on the outer perimeter of the injector face.
工程师几乎都会选择喷注高浓度燃料的方案 因为主燃烧室通常是富燃的
Engineers will almost always use fuel since the main combustion chamber usually runs fuel rich,
所以会有一整圈过量的燃料在外围流动
so there'll be a whole ring of extra fuel flowing around the outer perimeter
这些燃料不会遇到适量的氧化剂来反应
that won't have the right amount of oxidizer to react with.
这将产生一个更加富燃的环形燃烧区
This will produce a ring of even more fuel rich combustion,
阻止热量从主燃气向内壁传递
which prevents heat from transferring from the main combustion gases and the walls,
不仅如此 大多数靠近内壁的燃料根本不会参与反应
but not only that, most of the fuel closer to the walls won't react at all
因为根本没有足量的氧化剂
because it won't have any oxidizer to react with.
所以这些燃料会直接顺着燃烧室内壁流下来 形成一层膜
So it actually just travels down along the walls
of the combustion chamber and a film
夹在燃气与金属内壁之间
traps between the combusted gasses and the metal walls.
如果燃料是液体 那大概率会变成气态
And if it is a liquid, it will likely phase change from a liquid to a gas,
形成一个气体边界层
then that'll create a vapor boundary layer
在相变过程中还能吸收热量
as well as absorbed some heat energy in the process of phase changing.
假如发动机是再生冷却的 那么通常会直接在内壁上钻孔
It's common to actually drill holes in the walls, assuming they're regeneratively cooled,
故意让燃料泄露进来
to intentionally leak in some of the fuel,
尤其在一些关键发热部位 比如发动机的喉部
especially in particular hotspots, like the throat of the engine.
使用燃料进行液膜冷却的另一个奇怪的好处是
Another weird benefit of using fuel to cool
当使用RP-1之类的碳基燃料时 可以刚好以煤烟的形式在内壁形成碳层
is that you can create a carbon layer in the form of coking along the walls
when using a carbon-based fuel like RP-1.
当进行富燃燃烧时
When you have a fuel rich combustion,
大量的碳会不完全燃烧 形成煤烟
there's a lot of carbon that will be unburnt and can create soot.
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
观察视频中梅林发动机燃气发生器的废气
Just look at the exhaust of the gas generator for the Merlin engine.
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
为了降低温度 太空叉让燃气发生器内进行极度富燃的燃烧
SpaceX runs the combustion inside the gas generator extremely fuel rich
in order to reduce this temperature,
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
从而保护涡轮不被熔化 这点刚刚提到过
so the turbine doesn't melt, like we mentioned before.
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
可以看到排出的产物又浓又黑
As a by-product, you see the exhaust coming out is very, very dark and sooty.
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
这和可以附着在燃烧室内壁的煤烟是相同的物质
This is the same type of soot that can actually stick to the walls of the chamber
这种东西通常弊大于利 因为可能堵住喷注器
and often has a bad side effect, which is having that soot attached to the injectors
还可能堵住冷却口本身
and potentially the cooling holes or slots themselves, which can clog them up.
但附着在燃烧室内壁的煤烟则是一种有用的隔热罩
But the soot that sticks to the walls is another thermal barrier that can help.
我们继续听听Tom Markusic对此的解释
Again, let's hear Tom Markusic explaining that.
我当时还近距离参观了他们的Reaver发动机
We also saw great evidence of this soot
[搞发动机弄得满脸却黑]
我当时还近距离参观了他们的Reaver发动机
when we were up close and personal with their Reaver engines
弄得Tom像烧锅炉出来的一样
as evidenced by the soot on Tom's face.
-对于RP燃料 如果有产物附着在燃烧室内壁上
- Also with RP propellants, if some of the products that condense on the surface of the chamber
萤火虫太空公司
CEO
那么它对于防止热量传递到内壁上是有益的 - 原来如此
beneficial for inhibiting, heat transferred to the wall. - Right.
- 所以如果室压超过大约1200 PSI
- So once you get up about, above about 1200 PSI,
煤烟 就是那层碳 就开始脱落了
that sort of soot, carbon layer starts to come off,
一开始脱落 冷却情况就开始变差
so it kind of runs away, your cooling problems get worse,
这个情况是陡然发生的
very kind of precipitously as you go over that,
不是在比如100 PSI范围内慢慢发生的
it's not just 100 PSI is a little bit different,
因为煤烟掉干净了 大量热量会涌入内壁
cause your soot away and now you've got much more heat transferred to the wall.
所以利用煤烟进行隔热要考虑很多其他变量
So there are other factors that play into what's going on in there.
- 也就是说燃烧室内的煤烟可以充当类似隔热罩的作用吗?
- So the coking on the combustion chamber
can almost aid as like a, as an insulating barrier.
- 就是这样! - 真哒!
- It absolutely does.  - Really!
- 煤烟是一种免费又高效的隔热罩
- It's really effective thermal barrier coating for free.
你看我这满脸却黑 但发动机燃烧室可老喜欢这玩意了
So all that soot you saw on my face and that chamber that's great for thermal barrier coating.
顺便 强烈推荐大家看看我采访Tom的视频
By the way, if you haven't seen this interview with Tom, I highly recommend it.
Tom是实打实的火箭博士 有机械和航天工程的博士学位
Tom is literally a rocket doctor after all, having a PhD in mechanical and aerospace engineering.
简直学富五车
So it's packed full of great knowledge.
回到梅林发动机燃气发生器排出浓浓黑烟的话题中
But back to the Merlin engine with that really dark fuel rich exhaust from the gas generator.
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
这些废气还有其他用处
There's another thing we can do with that exhaust.
我们可以用它来冷却一部分喷管 但有一些注意事项
We can use the gas itself to film cool some of the nozzle, but there are a few caveats.
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
大家可以注意过海平面版本梅林发动机
You obviously noticed that on the sea level of Merlins
会直接在旁边排出废气
they are just dumping that exhaust overboard.
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
所以他们应该没有用这些气体来冷却什么东西
So it doesn't seem like they're cooling with that exhaust gas at all.
但如果我们看真空版梅林发动机
But if we pop over to the vacuum optimized Merlin,
就会发现其处理燃气发生器废气的方法有所不同
we can see they do something different with their gas generator exhaust.
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气歧管
它并没有直接在旁边排出废气
It isn't just simply dumped overboard,
而是把涡轮废气注入到了喷管为真空优化的扩张部分
instead that turbine exhaust gas is pumped into the nozzle extension
喷管延伸段
而是把涡轮废气注入到了喷管为真空优化的扩张部分
that makes the engine optimized for use in a vacuum.
想要理解此事 我们得先了解一些发动机喷管的知识
In order to understand why this makes sense, we do need to remember something about a nozzle.
当废气在发动机中经过喉部后
As it expands after the throat,
温度和压力都会随其流出喷管而越来越低
the exhaust gets cooler and lower pressure, the further down the nozzle you go.
因此当我们选取涡轮废气泵入点时要牢记这一点
So keep this in mind when we think about where we can pump in that turbine exhaust gas.
泵入点要足够远
It has to be far enough down a nozzle
不但要保证此处涡轮废气压强高于主燃烧室废气的压强
where it's both higher pressure than the main combustion exhaust
还要让涡轮废气可以成功形成薄膜 为喷管正常提供隔热效果
and it also needs to be at a point
F-1发动机喷管内部 再生冷却与膜冷却交界处
还要让涡轮废气可以成功形成薄膜 为喷管正常提供隔热效果
where the amount of heat it needs to protect the nozzle from
can successfully be insulated by the film cooling of the turbine exhaust gas
而该点通常是再生冷却的截止点
as regenerative cooling is often terminated at that point.
使用涡轮废气膜冷却的发动机的实例有土星五号上的发动机
Some other engines that did film cooling with their turbine exhaust
are the engines on the Saturn V.
上面搭载的F-1和J-2发动机都使用涡轮废气膜冷却
Both of them, actually, the F-1 and the J-2, utilized turbine exhaust film cooling
来为喷管底部降温
to keep the lower portions of their nozzles cool.
J-2发动机在歧管下还同时使用了再生冷却
In the case of the J-2, it still utilized re-gen cooling below the manifold,
而F-1发动机在歧管下就没有再生冷却参与了
but the F-1 stops doing re-gen cooling at the manifold
因为膜冷却已经足够保护剩余部分的喷管不被尾焰熔化了
because the film cooling was enough to keep the rest of the nozzle from melting.
F-1发动机在运行时还有一个很有意思的细节
There's a really fun and distinct thing to notice when the F-1s were running.
大家仔细看 明亮的橙色火焰不是在喷管口处就出现的
Notice the bright orange flame front doesn't actually start at the end of the nozzle.
而是在尾焰与喷口之间有一段奇怪的深色区域
There's this weird dark bit dancing round between the flame and the nozzle exit.
这就是涡轮废气形成的冷却气膜
That's the turbine exhaust film cooling gas.
因为废气极度富燃 需要一段时间和氧气结合并燃烧
Because it's so fuel rich, it takes a moment for it to find oxygen to burn with and ignite.
而废气离开发动机后就不存在这个问题了
This of course doesn't happen until outside the engine
因为废气可以和大气中的氧气反应
when it eventually will react with oxygen in our atmosphere.
我们还能在一款发动机中看到些许这种现象
But what's confusing is we can see a little bit of this
但奇怪的是 这款发动机是无燃气发生器的闭式循环
in a closed cycle rocket engine that doesn't have a gas generator
也就不存在涡轮废气排放到喷管这一操作
and therefore doesn't dump the exhaust gas into the nozzle.
说的就是你 Atlas V火箭的RD-180发动机
I mean, check out the RD-180 on the Atlas V.
喷口外也是有一段深色火焰 和F-1发动机很像
Notice there's little dark spikes leaving the nozzle, it's kind of similar to the F-1.
这是富燃的冷却膜 而不是燃气发生器废气
That's from the fuel rich film cooling and not gas generator exhaust soot.
不像F-1那样明显 但仍然可以观察到
It's not as prominent, but it's still quite noticeable,
但大家可能在其他一些发动机上也能看到颜色发暗的部分
but you might actually notice some dark spots in some other engines,
比如真空梅林发动机 或火箭实验室的真空Rutherford发动机
such as the vacuum optimized Merlin engine or Rocket Lab's vacuum optimized Rutherford engine.
火箭实验室的创始人兼CEO兼CTO Peter Beck在最近的采访中跟我提到过此事
Rocket Lab, founder, CEO and CTO Peter Beck
was talking to me about this in a recent interview.
- 有不少发动机都会进行一定程度的膜冷却
- You know, most engines, will run some film cooling, so there's a small amount of film cooling.
火箭实验室
CEO
实际上如果你们仔细看的话
And in fact, if you look at, we can actually,
就能注意到在很多上面级火箭发动机上
you can look at just about any rocket engine on an upper stage on a,
尾部的耐火中间合金喷管 铌喷管
like refractory middle alloy nozzle, like a niobium nozzle.
就能看到一些深色的区域
You can see the dark spots.
这些深色区围绕喷管底部一圈 像贴在喷管背后一样
So you'll notice it's kind of on a nozzle, there's this kind of dark spots that run around the periphery
有时一直到燃烧室喷注器的部分都是深色的
or those actually, you know, the locations of the injectors up in the thrust chamber.
而这些深色区域对应的就是冷却膜喷注器的位置
And that's where you can, that's where the film cooling injector kind of lies,
in line with one of those dark spots.
但大家注意真空梅林发动机和真空Rutherford发动机
But notice the vacuum optimized Merlin and vacuum optimized Rutherford
它们和其它发动机有一点不同
look a little different than the others.
在太空中运行时 他们的喷管延伸段都烧红了
When they're running in space, their nozzle extensions glow bright red.
怎么回事?
What the heck is going on here?
这说明金属已经被烧到红热状态 并正在向太空辐射热量
That is just the metal getting really hot and then radiating that heat out into space.
这就是冷却发动机的另一种方法
Well, this is another viable option, to keep your rocket engine from melting.
膜冷却
别忘了 辐射传热和传导/对流传热之间是有区别的
Don't forget, there's a difference between radiative heat transfer
and conductive or convective heat transfer.
太空中没有大气
Since there's no atmosphere in space,
所以没有任何空气能吸收热量进行传导或对流
there isn't any air to pick up and conduct or convect the heat.
因此你不能在发动机上贴个风扇来进行冷却 指望着把热量吹走
So it's not like you can just run a fan over your engine to keep it cool
and expect it to wave heat away.
唯一的选择就是将热量辐射出去
The only option here is to radiate the heat away.
与热对流或热传导不同 热辐射不需要介质来传递热量
Unlike convection or conduction, radiation doesn't need matter to transfer heat,
就像太阳可以通过热辐射在真空中传递热量一样
just like how the sun transfers heat through the vacuum of space via radiation.
真空梅林和Rutherford发动机的喷管延伸段是用一种非常薄的金属制成的
The nozzle extension in the vacuum optimized Merlin and Rutherford are made out of a very thin metal.
通常是一些合金 如铌合金 或其他一些耐高温的材料
Usually some alloys, such as niobium alloy, or some other material
that can withstand high heat loads.
但是铌合金喷管延伸段的问题是它非常薄 而且相对脆弱
Now, the problem with say the niobium nozzle extension
is it's very thin and relatively fragile,
但更大的问题是铌易与氧气发生反应
but even more problematic is how reactive niobium is to oxygen.
所以使用铌合金的发动机基本只能在真空中运行
This means engines with niobium can really only operate in a vacuum.
这也意味着它们的制造要困难得多
And it also means their manufacturing is much more difficult.
另一个使用铌喷管延伸段的著名发动机是阿波罗服务舱上的AJ10发动机
Another famous engine that used a niobium nozzle extension
阿波罗服务舱发动机测试
另一个使用铌喷管延伸段的著名发动机是阿波罗服务舱上的AJ10发动机
was the AJ10 on the Apollo service module.
下面深色部分就是铌合金
That dark part is niobium.
而且还好它从来没掉过链子
And it's a good thing that engine worked well
不然阿波罗宇航员们就只能留在月球轨道上绕圈了
because otherwise it could have left Apollo astronauts stranded orbiting the moon.
到这里基本就差不多了
Okay, I think that pretty much does it.
火箭推进工程师们肯定还有些其他有趣的小妙招
I'm sure there's some other fun tricks propulsion engineers employ,
但主流方案基本就是这些了
but that's really the main ones.
看到工程师们如何选择最适合他们的发动机的冷却系统真的很有意思
And it's really fun to see how engineers choose which systems work best for their engines.
但我认为 想要复习今天的内容
But I think to review this topic best,
最好的办法是再来看看真空梅林发动机
let's just look at the vacuum optimized Merlin one more time
因为它几乎把每种方法都用上了
because it employs almost every type of cooling.
在燃气发生器上 它既使用了热沉冷却 排出的还是富燃废气
At the gas generator, we see both heat sink tactics and a very fuel rich exhaust employed.
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
原因是其他冷却方法其实很难用在旋转的涡轮上
This makes sense because the other forms of cooling can't be utilized on spinning turbines.
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
你只能使用高温金属材料
You just have to use high temperature metals
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
并降低废气温度才能保证温度不会超过金属可承受的范围
and then lower the exhaust temperatures to make sure it doesn't get hotter
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气
并降低废气温度才能保证温度不会超过金属可承受的范围
than those metals can handle.
太空叉还在室壁 喉部和喷管上部使用再生冷却
SpaceX uses regenerative cooling
for the chamber walls, throat, and the first bit of the nozzle.
同时在发动机内部 他们还用额外的燃料在燃烧室与喉部附近使用膜冷却
Then inside the engine, they employ some film cooling with additional fuel
in the chamber and near the throat.
还使用燃气发生器的废气为喷管延伸段 即再生冷却截至的部分提供膜冷却
They also use film cooling from the gas generator exhaust at the nozzle extension
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气歧管
还使用燃气发生器的废气为喷管延伸段 即再生冷却截至的部分提供膜冷却
when the regenerative cooling channels end.
但除了膜冷却外
But in addition to the film cooling,
喷管延伸段还使用薄而耐高温的铌合金来辐射额外的热量
the nozzle extension also radiates additional heat away
喷管延伸段
喷管延伸段还使用薄而耐高温的铌合金来辐射额外的热量
by using a thin, but high temperature niobium alloy.
真空梅林发动机目前来看唯一没有使用的是烧蚀冷却
The only form of cooling the vacuum optimized Merlin
doesn't appear to use is ablative cooling.
但既然他们的上面级只能一次性使用
But considering the upper stages are only used once,
如果需要的话 他们的确可以为这款发动机增加一些烧蚀冷却的部分
this is one engine that could probably get away with a little ablative cooling in a spot
if they needed to.
我很欣赏工程师们为防止火箭发动机熔化而想出的各种小妙招
I love all these little tricks that engineers have figured out to keep rocket engines from melting.
再生冷却
我觉得再生成冷却的工作方式真的让我大开眼界
It blows my mind that re-gen cooling works for some reason.
用涡轮废气冷却喷管的操作也让我大呼精妙
And also that you can use exhaust gas from the turbine to film cool your nozzle too,
燃气发生器
燃气发生器废气歧管
乍一看 两种技术感觉都是如此离谱
for some reason, both of those things just seem kind of crazy
喷管延伸段
但却又如此好用
and it's amazing that they work so well.
大家还有什么问题吗 欢迎在评论区讨论
Let me know if you have any other questions
还可以分享一些你们知道的有趣内容
or maybe let me know if you learned something cool, literally,
或者希望未来还想看到哪些内容 也可以说说
or if you have ideas for upcoming videos in the comments below.
后面就是恰饭/推广啦~
I owe a huge thank you to my Patreon supporters for helping make videos like this possible.
If you want to help me continue to do what I do, head on over to patreon.com/everydayastronaut,
where you'll gain access to our exclusive Discord channel,
some exclusive live streams and even early access to some videos as well.
Again, that's patreon.com/everydayastronaut.
And while you're online, be sure and head over to our web store
for shirts like this, the brand new RD-171 shirt,
that if you watch the Soviet rocket engine video, you know this is one of the coolest engines,
this is now one of my favorite shirts.
But be sure and check out some of our other cool stuff too,
such as our space shuttle ejection hoodie,
our brand new RS-25 shirt or our schematics collection of our future martial shirt,
lots of really cool stuff over at everydayastronaut.com/shop.
感谢大家的观看
Thanks everybody. That's gonna do it for me.
我是《天天太空人》的Tim Dodd 将太空带入寻常百姓家~
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut, bringing space down to earth for everyday people.